[
    {
        "id": "GATE2003-CS-Q34",
        "year": 2003,
        "questionNumber": 34,
        "subject": "Discrete Mathematics",
        "topic": "Balls In Bins",
        "questionType": "MCQ",
        "question": "m identical balls are to be placed in n distinct bags. You are given that m â‰¥ kn, where k is a natural number > 1. In how many ways can the balls be placed in the bags if each bag must contain at least k balls?",
        "options": [
            "$m - k$",
            "$\\binom{m-kn+n-1}{n-1}$",
            "$\\binom{m-1}{n-k}$",
            "$\\binom{m-kn+n+k-2}{n-k}$"
        ],
        "correctAnswer": [
            1
        ],
        "answerText": null,
        "difficulty": "normal",
        "marks": 1,
        "tags": [
            "combinatory",
            "balls-in-bins"
        ],
        "source": "GATE CSE 2003",
        "sourceURL": null,
        "addedBy": "Answer key",
        "verified": true,
        "explanation": "https://gateoverflow.in/924/gate-cse-2003-question-34",
        "metadata": {
            "set": "CS",
            "paperType": "official",
            "language": "English"
        }
    },
    {
        "id": "GATE2022-CS-Q22",
        "year": 2022,
        "questionNumber": 22,
        "subject": "Discrete Mathematics",
        "topic": "Balls In Bins",
        "questionType": "Numerical Answer",
        "question": "The number of arrangements of six identical balls in three identical bins is",
        "options": [],
        "correctAnswer": [],
        "answerText": "7",
        "difficulty": "normal",
        "marks": 1,
        "tags": [
            "combinatory",
            "balls-in-bins"
        ],
        "source": "GATE CSE 2022",
        "sourceURL": null,
        "addedBy": "Answer key",
        "verified": true,
        "explanation": "https://gateoverflow.in/371914/gate-cse-2022-question-22",
        "metadata": {
            "set": "CS",
            "paperType": "official",
            "language": "English"
        }
    },
    {
        "id": "GATE2004-IT-Q35",
        "year": 2004,
        "questionNumber": 35,
        "subject": "Discrete Mathematics",
        "topic": "Balls In Bins",
        "questionType": "MCQ",
        "question": "In how many ways can we distribute 5 distinct balls, $B_1, B_2, \\dots , B_5$ in 5 distinct cells, $C_1, C_2, \\dots ,C_5$ such that Ball $B_i$ is not in cell $C_i$, $\\forall i = 1, 2, \\dots 5$ and each cell contains exactly one ball?",
        "options": [
            "44",
            "96",
            "120",
            "3125"
        ],
        "correctAnswer": [0],
        "answerText": "44",
        "difficulty": "normal",
        "marks": null,
        "tags": [
            "combinatory",
            "balls-in-bins"
        ],
        "source": "GATE IT 2004",
        "sourceURL": null,
        "addedBy": "Answer key",
        "verified": true,
        "explanation": "https://gateoverflow.in/3678/gate-it-2004-question-35",
        "metadata": {
            "set": "IT",
            "paperType": "official",
            "language": "English"
        }
    },
    {
        "id": "GATE1990-CS-Q3-iii",
        "year": 1990,
        "questionNumber": 3.3,
        "subject": "Discrete Mathematics",
        "topic": "Combinatory",
        "questionType": "Multiple Select Question",
        "question": "The number of rooted binary trees with n nodes is,",
        "options": [
            "Equal to the number of ways of multiplying (n + 1) matrices.",
            "Equal to the number of ways of arranging n. out of 2n distinct elements.",
            "Equal to $\\frac{1}{n+1} \\binom{2n}{n}$.",
            "Equal to n!."
        ],
        "correctAnswer": [
            0,
            2
        ],
        "answerText": null,
        "difficulty": "normal",
        "marks": null,
        "tags": [
            "combinatory",
            "catalan number"
        ],
        "source": "GATE CSE 1990",
        "sourceURL": null,
        "addedBy": "Answer key",
        "verified": true,
        "explanation": "https://gateoverflow.in/84060/gate-cse-1990-question-3-iii",
        "metadata": {
            "set": "CS",
            "paperType": "official",
            "language": "English"
        }
    },
    {
        "id": "GATE1990-CS-Q3-ix",
        "year": 1990,
        "questionNumber": 3.9,
        "subject": "Discrete Mathematics",
        "topic": "Combinatory",
        "questionType": "MCQ",
        "question": "The number of ways in which 5 A's, 5 B's and 5 C's can be arranged in a row is:",
        "options": [
            "$\\frac{15!}{(5!)^3}$",
            "$15!$",
            "$\\binom{15}{5}$",
            "$15!{(5!3!)}$"
        ],
        "correctAnswer": [
            0
        ],
        "answerText": null,
        "difficulty": "normal",
        "marks": null,
        "tags": [
            "combinatory"
        ],
        "source": "GATE CSE 1990",
        "sourceURL": null,
        "addedBy": "Answer key",
        "verified": true,
        "explanation": null,
        "metadata": {
            "set": "CS",
            "paperType": "official",
            "language": "English"
        }
    },
    {
        "id": "GATE1998-CS-Q1.23",
        "year": 1998,
        "questionNumber": 1.23,
        "subject": "Discrete Mathematics",
        "topic": "Combinatory",
        "questionType": "MCQ",
        "question": "How many sub strings of different lengths (non-zero) can be formed from a character\nstring of length n?",
        "options": [
            "n",
            "$n^2$",
            "$2^n$",
            "$\\frac{n(n+1)}{2}$"
        ],
        "correctAnswer": [
            3
        ],
        "answerText": null,
        "difficulty": "normal",
        "marks": null,
        "tags": [
            "combinatory"
        ],
        "source": "GATE CSE 1998",
        "sourceURL": null,
        "addedBy": "Answer key",
        "verified": false,
        "explanation": null,
        "metadata": {
            "set": "CS",
            "paperType": "official",
            "language": "English"
        }
    },
    {
        "id": "GATE1999-CS-Q1.3",
        "year": 1999,
        "questionNumber": 1.3,
        "subject": "Discrete Mathematics",
        "topic": "Combinatory",
        "questionType": "MCQ",
        "question": "The number of binary strings of n zeros and k ones in which no two ones are adjacent is",
        "options": [
            "$\\binom{n-1}{k}$",
            "$\\binom{n+1}{k}$",
            "$\\binom{n+1}{k+1}$",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "correctAnswer": [
            1
        ],
        "answerText": null,
        "difficulty": "normal",
        "marks": null,
        "tags": [
            "combinatory"
        ],
        "source": "GATE CSE 1999",
        "sourceURL": null,
        "addedBy": "Answer key",
        "verified": false,
        "explanation": null,
        "metadata": {
            "set": "CS",
            "paperType": "official",
            "language": "English"
        }
    },
    {
        "id": "GATE1999-CS-Q2.2",
        "year": 1999,
        "questionNumber": 2.2,
        "subject": "Discrete Mathematics",
        "topic": "Combinatory",
        "questionType": "MCQ",
        "question": "Two girls have picked 10 roses, 15 sunflowers and 15 daffodils. What is the number of\nways they can divide the flowers among themselves?",
        "options": [
            "1638",
            "2100",
            "2640",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "correctAnswer": [
            2
        ],
        "answerText": null,
        "difficulty": "normal",
        "marks": null,
        "tags": [
            "combinatory"
        ],
        "source": "GATE CSE 1999",
        "sourceURL": null,
        "addedBy": "Answer key",
        "verified": false,
        "explanation": null,
        "metadata": {
            "set": "CS",
            "paperType": "official",
            "language": "English"
        }
    },
    {
        "id": "GATE2000-CS-Q5",
        "year": 2000,
        "questionNumber": 5,
        "subject": "Discrete Mathematics",
        "topic": "Combinatory",
        "questionType": "Descriptive",
        "question": "A multiset is an unordered collection of elements where elements may repeat any\nnumber of times. The size of a multiset is the number of elements in it, counting\nrepetitions.\n\na. What is the number of multisets of size 4 that can be constructed from n distinct elements so\nthat at least one element occurs exactly twice?\nb. How many multisets can be constructed from n distinct elements?",
        "options": [],
        "correctAnswer": [],
        "answerText": null,
        "difficulty": "normal",
        "marks": null,
        "tags": [
            "combinabory"
        ],
        "source": "GATE CSE 2000",
        "sourceURL": null,
        "addedBy": "Answer key",
        "verified": false,
        "explanation": null,
        "metadata": {
            "set": "CS",
            "paperType": "official",
            "language": "English"
        }
    },
    {
        "id": "GATE2001-CS-Q2.1",
        "year": 2001,
        "questionNumber": 2.1,
        "subject": "Discrete Mathematics",
        "topic": "Combinatory",
        "questionType": "MCQ",
        "question": "How many 4-digit even numbers have all 4 digits distinct?",
        "options": [
            "2240",
            "2296",
            "2620",
            "4536"
        ],
        "correctAnswer": [
            0
        ],
        "answerText": null,
        "difficulty": "normal",
        "marks": 4,
        "tags": [
            "combinabory"
        ],
        "source": "GATE CSE 2001",
        "sourceURL": null,
        "addedBy": "Answer key",
        "verified": false,
        "explanation": null,
        "metadata": {
            "set": "CS",
            "paperType": "official",
            "language": "English"
        }
    },
    {
        "id": "GATE2003-CS-Q4",
        "year": 2003,
        "questionNumber": 4,
        "subject": "Discrete Mathematics",
        "topic": "Combinatory",
        "questionType": "MCQ",
        "question": "Let A be a sequence of 8 distinct integers sorted in ascending order. How many distinct\npairs of sequences, B and C are there such that\n\ni. each is sorted in ascending order,\nii. B has 5 and C has 3 elements, and\niii. the result of merging B and C gives A",
        "options": [
            "2",
            "219",
            "210",
            "$20C10 - 8 C4 \\times 1 C5$"
        ],
        "correctAnswer": [
            0
        ],
        "answerText": null,
        "difficulty": "normal",
        "marks": null,
        "tags": [
            "combinabory"
        ],
        "source": "GATE CSE 2003",
        "sourceURL": null,
        "addedBy": "Answer key",
        "verified": false,
        "explanation": null,
        "metadata": {
            "set": "CS",
            "paperType": "official",
            "language": "English"
        }
    },
    {
        "id": "GATE2003-CS-Q5",
        "year": 2003,
        "questionNumber": 5,
        "subject": "Discrete Mathematics",
        "topic": "Combinatory",
        "questionType": "MCQ",
        "question": "n couples are invited to a party with the condition that every husband should be\naccompanied by his wife. However, a wife need not be accompanied by her husband.\nThe number of different gatherings possible at the party is",
        "options": [
            "$2^n C_n \\times 2^{n-1}$",
            "$3^n$",
            "56",
            "$2^n C_n$"
        ],
        "correctAnswer": [
            1
        ],
        "answerText": null,
        "difficulty": "normal",
        "marks": 4,
        "tags": [
            "combinatory"
        ],
        "source": "GATE CSE 2003",
        "sourceURL": null,
        "addedBy": "Answer key",
        "verified": false,
        "explanation": null,
        "metadata": {
            "set": "CS",
            "paperType": "official",
            "language": "English"
        }
    },
    {
        "id": "GATE2004-CS-Q75",
        "year": 2004,
        "questionNumber": 75,
        "subject": "Discrete Mathematics",
        "topic": "Combinatory",
        "questionType": "MCQ",
        "question": "Mala has the colouring book in which each English letter is drawn two times. She wants drels\nto paint each of these 52 prints with one of k colours, such that the colour pairs used to\ncolour any two letters are different. Both prints of a letter can also be coloured with the same\ncolour. What is the minimum value of k that satisfies this requirement?",
        "options": [
            "9",
            "8",
            "7",
            "6"
        ],
        "correctAnswer": [
            2
        ],
        "answerText": null,
        "difficulty": "normal",
        "marks": 4,
        "tags": [
            "combinaory"
        ],
        "source": "GATE CSE 2004",
        "sourceURL": null,
        "addedBy": "Answer key",
        "verified": false,
        "explanation": null,
        "metadata": {
            "set": "CS",
            "paperType": "official",
            "language": "English"
        }
    },
    {
        "id": "GATE2007-CS-Q84",
        "year": 2007,
        "questionNumber": 84,
        "subject": "Discrete Mathematics",
        "topic": "Combinatory",
        "questionType": "MCQ",
        "question": "Suppose that a robot is placed on the Cartesian plane. At each step it is allowed to move\neither one unit up or one unit right, i.e., if it is at (i, j) then it can move to either (i + 1, j)\nor (i,j+1).\nHow many distinct paths are there for the robot to reach the point (10, 10) starting from the\ninitial position (0, 0)?",
        "options": [
            "$20 C_{10}$"
        ],
        "correctAnswer": [
            0
        ],
        "answerText": null,
        "difficulty": "normal",
        "marks": 4,
        "tags": [
            "combinabory"
        ],
        "source": "GATE CSE 2007",
        "sourceURL": null,
        "addedBy": "Answer key",
        "verified": false,
        "explanation": null,
        "metadata": {
            "set": "CS",
            "paperType": "official",
            "language": "English"
        }
    },
    {
        "id": "GATE2007-CS-Q85",
        "year": 2007,
        "questionNumber": 85,
        "subject": "Discrete Mathematics",
        "topic": "Combinatory",
        "questionType": "MCQ",
        "question": "Suppose that a robot is placed on the Cartesian plane. At each step it is allowed to move 2ey\neither one unit up or one unit right, i.e., if it is at (i, j) then it can move to either (i + 1, j)\nor (i,j+1).\n\nSuppose that the robot is not allowed to traverse the line segment from (4, 4) to (5, 4). With this\nconstraint, how many distinct paths are there for the robot to reach (10, 10) starting from\n(0,0)?",
        "options": [
            "29",
            "$8C4 \\times 11 C5$"
        ],
        "correctAnswer": [
            1
        ],
        "answerText": null,
        "difficulty": "normal",
        "marks": 4,
        "tags": [
            "combinatory",
            "discrete-mathematics"
        ],
        "source": "GATE CSE 2007",
        "sourceURL": null,
        "addedBy": "Answer key",
        "verified": false,
        "explanation": null,
        "metadata": {
            "set": "CS",
            "paperType": "official",
            "language": "English"
        }
    },
    {
        "id": "GATE2014-CS-Set1-Q",
        "year": 2014,
        "questionNumber": null,
        "subject": "Discrete Mathematics",
        "topic": "Combinatory",
        "questionType": "Numerical Answer",
        "question": "A pennant is a sequence of numbers, each number being 1 or 2. An n-pennant is a\nsequence of numbers with sum equal to n. For example, (1, 1, 2) is a 4-pennant. The\nset of all possible 1-pennants is (1), the set of all possible 2-pennants is (2), (1, 1) and the\nset of all 3-pennants is (2,1), (1,1,1), (1,2). Note that the pennant (1,2) is not the same as\nthe pennant (2,1). The number of 10-pennants is",
        "options": [],
        "correctAnswer": [],
        "answerText": "89",
        "difficulty": "normal",
        "marks": 1,
        "tags": [
            "combinabory"
        ],
        "source": "GATE CSE 2014 Set 1",
        "sourceURL": null,
        "addedBy": "Answer key",
        "verified": false,
        "explanation": null,
        "metadata": {
            "set": "CS",
            "paperType": "official",
            "language": "English"
        }
    },
    {
        "id": "GATE2015-CS-Set3-Q5",
        "year": 2015,
        "questionNumber": 5,
        "subject": "Discrete Mathematics",
        "topic": "Combinatory",
        "questionType": "Numerical Answer",
        "question": "The number of 4 digit numbers having their digits in non-decreasing order (from left to\nright) constructed by using the digits belonging to the set {1, 2, 3} is",
        "options": [],
        "correctAnswer": [],
        "answerText": "15",
        "difficulty": "normal",
        "marks": 1,
        "tags": [
            "combinabory"
        ],
        "source": "GATE CSE 2015 Set 3",
        "sourceURL": null,
        "addedBy": "Answer key",
        "verified": false,
        "explanation": null,
        "metadata": {
            "set": "CS",
            "paperType": "official",
            "language": "English"
        }
    }
]